Guide to the Bob Brown Oral History Project 2005-2010
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
- Interview with Clyde Hawks, 5 June 2005; OH 396-026; Sound Recording, digital, 64.5 MB, Wav; Transcript, 31 leaves
  Hawks, speaker of the Montana House of Representatives in 1961, discusses his first congressional race in 1948 and many of the politicians he served with, the influence of the Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company on state politics and the lobbyists who worked for them, the establishment of the prison ranch in Deer Lodge, the peyote bill, Yellowtail Dam bill, Montana Stock Growers Association, the Public Utility District bill, and Montana governors and other politicians he served with in the House
- Interview with John H. Leuthold, 6 July 2005; OH 396-027; Sound Recording, digital, 444 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Leuthold provides his recollections of former governors such as Nutter, Babcock, Schwinden and influential legislators during his term in the Montana House of Representatives, 1950-1968. He also recalls his experience in the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention.
- Interview with Leslie Eskildsen, 8 July 2005; OH 396-028; Sound Recording, digital, 71.5 MB, Wav; Transcript, 36 leaves
  Eskildsen explains his personal relationships with prominent Montana legislators, congressmen, and governors especially during his terms in the Montana House of Representatives from 1954 to 1964. He describes issues with the Montana State Penitentiary in Deer Lodge. He recalls his experience in the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention and specific issues of the time.
- Interview with Antoinette Fraser Rosell, 6 July 2005; OH 396-029; Sound Recording, digital, 55.5 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Fraser Rosell, a former Montana legislator, describes influences leading to her party affiliation, her early legislative work, and relationships with other members of the Montana legislature. She recalls the trend in female interest in politics while she was in the legislature. She compares the new and old state constitutions.
- Interview with William Mathers, 7 July 2005; OH 396-030; Sound Recording, digital, 405 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Mathers, a former Montana legislator and Senate president, describes how he became interested in and involved with politics in Montana. He compares and contrasts the state government and parties of Texas and Montana and their influence over his party affiliation. He recalls partisan issues that were fought in the legislature including public utility districts, budget cuts, Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company influences, and the sales tax. He recalls strong legislators and governors, as well as his work on the Board of Regents for the state university system.
- Interview with Edward Smith, 7 July 2005; OH 396-031; Sound Recording, digital, 71 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Smith, a former Montana legislator, describes his involvement on important legislation, the Wheat Commission, resolving the rural electricity issue by amending a previous bill, and participation in the Senate Finance Commission in Montana. He gives his impressions of former governors, legislators, and running for governor.
- Interview with Magnus Aasheim, 7 July 2005; OH 396-032; Sound Recording, digital, 407 MB, Wav; Transcript, 28 leaves
  Aasheim, a former Montana legislator and delegate to the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention, describes his initial interest in politics, his first campaign for the election to the House of Representatives in 1959, his first legislative session, and his experiences during the Montana Constitutional Convention. He discusses the various governors that he served with and his impressions of influential legislators.
- Interview with Eugene C. Tidball, 1 October 2005; OH 396-033; Sound Recording, digital, 366 MB, Wav; Transcript, 25 leaves
  Raised in Billings, Montana, Tidball, the first director of Montana Legislative Council, 1960s lawyer and lobbyist for the Anaconda Company, attended The University of Montana from 1949-1955, graduating with degrees in business and law. He discusses his work as the first director of the Montana Legislative Council, which attempted to make the legislative process more modern, functional and efficient. From there, he assesses legislators who stood out to him. Tidball began working as a lawyer and sometime-lobbyist for the Anaconda Company in 1965. He describes other Anaconda lawyers, lobbyists, and key company players, as well as lobbying strategies (including the use of a hospitality room). He finishes by describing some reasons for the waning power and influence of the company in the 1970s, the sale of the company to Atlantic Richfield Company, and the closing of the mine.
- Interview with Tom Rolfe, 27 September 2005; OH 396-034; Sound Recording, digital, 326 MB, Wav; Transcript, 19 leaves
  Rolfe, a former Montana legislator and conservative leader, discusses how he became interested in politics as a youth, his continued activity as a teenager and young adult, and finally his role at the Republican National Convention of 1975, where he sought to nominate Ronald Reagan for president. Rolfe discusses this convention and his views on Ronald Reagan at length.
- Interview with James Mockler, 28 September 2005; OH 396-035; Sound Recording, digital, 213 MB, Wav; Transcript, 15 leaves
  Mockler, a former Montana legislator and lobbyist for the mining industry, describes his background in Wyoming and moves on to the effects of Montana and Wyoming’s coal taxes in 1975. Mockler details the effect of the coal tax on Montana’s coal business contracts, his relationship with Governor Schwinden and the “window of opportunity.” He ends with his opinion of coal bed methane development
- Interview with Orvin Fjare, 20 January 2005; OH 396-036; Sound Recording, digital, 189 MB, Wav; Transcript, 12 leaves
  Fjare, a former Montana legislator, begins by describing how he became interested in politics. He explains how the Anaconda Company’s support helped him get elected to the U.S. Congress in 1954. Later he describes how the Anaconda Company’s intense oversight and pressure led him to break off the relationship. Fjare discusses his relationships with Presidents Eisenhower, Nixon, and Ford. He describes his involvement with the Yellowtail Dam project and other major issues during his time in Congress
- Interview with Louise Galt and Jack Galt, 3 December 2005; OH 396-037; Sound Recording, digital, 413 MB, Wav; Transcript, 39 leaves
  Mr. Galt is a state senator, president of state senate, and Republican national committeeman while Mrs. Galt was a young county attorney in Fergus County, active in Republican politics, and was the widow of Wellington Rankin. The couple discusses their families’ backgrounds in Montana politics and their own evolving political awareness and activity. Each gives their impressions of governors and legislators in Montana, as well as the role of the Anaconda Company in state politics. Louise talks extensively about the activities of her late husband, Wellington Rankin, attorney general, state Supreme Court justice, and brother of Jeannette Rankin.
- Interview with Stan Stephens, 17 November 2005; OH 396-038; Sound Recording, digital, 378 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Stan Stephens is a broadcast journalist and recipient of the Edward R. Murrow Prize, state senator, and former Republican governor of Montana. An immigrant from Canada, Stephens begins the interview with a description of his career in broadcast journalism. In 1969, he was elected to the state senate and served for 16 years before running for governor, an office he held from 1989-1993. Other topics include his political campaigns and his tenure as governor, with reference to the 1972 Constitutional Convention, coal and sales tax, education (including vocational), lobbyists, budgetary issues, and Native American reservations and social issues. Stephens gives his impressions of a number of legislators, governors, lobbyists, and presidents.
- Interview with Jean A. Turnage, 3 January 2006; OH 396-039; Sound Recording, digital, 371 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Former Montana State Supreme Court Chief Justice Turnage describes his past involvement in law and his inspirations to run for public offices. He describes his time in the legislature, introduced bills, and ends by describing his work in the Montana State Supreme Court. He explains generally how cases are heard at the Supreme Court as well as specific incidents.
- Interview with Thomas Towe, 10 February 2006; OH 396-040; Sound Recording, digital, 832 MB, Wav; Transcript, 59 leaves
  Towe, former Montana legislator, begins by telling various stories about the Montana Copper Kings and the Anaconda Company. This leads to his lengthy discussion on the development of the coal tax bill and the coal trust fund. He recollects various events and issues during his time in the legislature.
- Interview with Jake Frank, OH 396-041; Sound Recording, digital, MB, Wav; Transcript, 31 leaves
  Frank, a former Montana legislator, describes issues in the legislature including rural electric co-ops and the Anaconda Company. He ends by describing his work in the Rural Electrification Association and the Farmers Union and Farmers Home Association and issues in agriculture.
- Interview with Alfred Lewis Bishop, 17 August 2007; OH 396-042; Sound Recording, digital, 466 MB, Wav; Transcript, 31 leaves
  Bishop, a former Montana legislator and Fish and Game commissioner, describes issues he encountered while he was with the Fish and Game. He recalls anecdotes during his earlier years as a Billings attorney and other influential lawyers. He describes his various campaigns for the legislature and for the Republican primary for governor. He ends by describing his relationships with previous governors and speculates on the future of Montana.
- Interview with Neil Lynch, 16 November 2007; OH 396-043; Sound Recording, digital, 425 MB, Wav; Transcript, 34 leaves
  Lynch, a former Montana legislator, discusses his career in politics including the Anaconda Company, the Montana Power Company, his relationships with governors Forrest Anderson, Tom Judge, Stan Stephens, and other influential legislators, and issues of the time including sales tax, term limits, the Constitutional Convention, lobbyists, and foreign investments.
- Interview with Jack Schlitz, 17 Sepetember 2007; OH 396-044; Sound Recording, digital, 386 MB, Wav; Transcript, 29 leaves
  Schiltz, a former Montana legislator, describes the influence of the Montana Power Company and the Anaconda Company on Montana politics during the 1950s and his work at the Montana Constitutional Convention.
- Interview with Karl Ohs, 4 August 2007; OH 396-045; Sound Recording, digital, 263 MB, Wav; Transcript, 21 leaves
  Karl Ohs, former Lieutenant Governor, legislator, and FBI negotiator at the Freemen standoff provides an in depth look at his involvement as a negotiator during the Freemen standoff near Jordan, Montana, in 1996, the Freeman trial, and the aftermath.
- Interview withTed Schwinden, 18 August 2007; OH 396-046; Sound Recording, digital, 474 MB, Wav; Transcript, 26 leaves
  Schwinden, a former Montana legislator and governor from 1981-1989, begins by describing his growing interest in politics during high school and his activity in Roosevelt County, Montana. He discusses the legislature and provides stories about his dealings with other former governors and legislators including Forrest Anderson, Tim Babcock, Tom Judge, and Stan Stephens. He offers his perspective on issues such as the Resource Indemnity Trust, university funding, and gerrymandering. He ends by describing how Montana has changed over a century and possibilities for the future.
- Interview with Bill Norman, 26 May 2006; OH 396-047; Sound Recording, digital, 435 MB, Wav; Transcript, 33 leaves
  Norman, a Montana legislator from 1970-1990, recalls growing up in Minnesota and the earliest political influences that led him to become a Democrat. He credits his first political interest and activity with interest in Minnesotan Gene McCarthy, a U.S. senator. He discusses the legislature and provides stories about his dealings with other former governors and legislators including Dorothy Bradley, Thomas Towe, Luke McKeon, Jim Murray (lobbyist), Forrest Anderson, Tom Judge, Ted Schwinden, and Stan Stephens. He offers his perspective on issues such as coal development, the coal tax, abortion and the future of Montana.
- Interview with Thomas Judge, 18 August 2006; OH 396-048; Sound Recording, digital, 433 MB, Wav; Transcript, 29 leaves
  Judge, the Montana governor from 1972 to 1980, describes how he became interested in politics as a young man and his eventual election to the legislature. He describes the influence of the Anaconda Company and the Montana Power Company, coal development, the Federal Strip Mine Reclamation Act, and the Constitutional Convention. He explains his relationships with governors and legislators including Forrest Anderson, Tim Babcock, Ted Schwinden, Lee Metcalf, John Melcher, and Mike Mansfield. He ends with his opinion on Montana's future.
- Interview with Jim Murray, 11 October 2006; OH 396-049; Sound Recording, digital, 491 MB, Wav; Transcript, 33 leaves
  Murray, a former leader in Montana AFL/CIO and related labor unions, discusses his involvement with the AFL/CIO from 1968-1991, the labor movement in Montana, and worker’s rights. He discusses various influential leaders including Lee Metcalf, Mike Mansfield, Arnold Olsen, and Chet Blaylock
- Interview with Dorothy Eck, 22 May 2007; OH 396-050; Sound Recording, digital, 484 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Eck, a member of the League of Women Voters, a 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention delegate, and Montana legislator for five terms, 1980-2000, explains the events that guided her interests in politics, her eventual membership and presidency of the Montana League of Women Voters and discusses issues backed by that organization. She discusses her experience in the Montana Senate, 1980-2000, and describes former political leaders such as Mike Mansfield, Lee Metcalf, Arnold Olsen, and various influential legislators. At the end of the interview, she gives a detailed account of her participation in the Montana Constitutional Convention.
- Interview with Harrison Fagg, 29 March 2008; OH 396-051; Sound Recording, digital, 349 MB, Wav; Transcript, 49 leaves
  Fagg, a former Montana legislator (1968-1984) of Billings, Montana, recalls his family’s political nature and that influence on his political philosophy, his involvement with the Junior Chamber of Commerce, and his eventual relationship with Congressman Jim Batten. He explains his initial reactions to being in the legislature, relationships with various legislators, and legislation for the environmental movement. Specific issues include the Hard Rock Mining Bill, a sales tax campaign, a proposed coal moratorium, and the League of Towns and Cities.
- Interview with Lloyd C. “Sonny” Lockrem, 29 March 2008; OH 396-052; Sound Recording, digital, 426 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Lockrem, from Billings, Montana, is a former Montana legislator (1971-1981) and lobbyist for the Montana Contractors Association. He recalls experiences in the Marine Corp and working in a family construction business that peaked his interest in politics and running for the legislature. He details his relationships with former lobbyists, particularly from the Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company, and former Governor Tom Judge. He also explains the effect of single-member districts, implemented by the 1972 Constitutional Convention, on Yellowstone County politics. Other specifics include a proposed sales tax bill, the Anaconda Company, Governor Tom Judge, and natural resources.
- Interview with Bob Marks, 11 January 2008; OH 396-053; Sound Recording, digital, 428 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Marks, of Helena, Montana, is a former state legislator of Jefferson County (1969-1989) and former Speaker of the House in Montana. He describes becoming interested in politics early and his affiliation with the Republican Party. He contrasts his campaign for election to the House of Representatives with today’s process and he describes his first impressions of the legislature and of influential politicians. He discusses territorial integrity, coal mining, the influence of the Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company, and his relationship with various lobbyists. Marks ends with his impressions of various Governors Judge, Anderson, Stephens, and Schwinden, and their administrations and the future of Montana.
- Interview with Judy Paynter, 1 August 2008; OH 396-054; Sound Recording, digital, 687 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Paynter, a former legislative fiscal analyst and deputy budget director, discusses her experiences with financial affairs in the Montana legislature over more than 25 years. She explains her fiscal responsibilities including budget preparation, tax increases, and revenue estimation. She compares the administrations of Governors Schwinden, Stephens, Racicot, Martz, and Schweitzer, and the general effectiveness of each.
- Interview with Dave Lewis, 22 August 2008; OH 396-055; Sound Recording, digital, 645 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Lewis, a former budget analyst and Montana legislator, describes his 40 year participation in politics including his work as budget director, campaign contributor, director of the Department of Administration, director of the State Board of Investments, and as a member of the Montana legislature where he served as chairman of the House Appropriations Committee. Lewis discusses the pros and cons of being a partisan politician and reflects on changing governmental trends in Montana. Lewis maintains some focus on Governors Judge, Schwinden, Stephens, Racicot and Martz; their agendas; and conflicts during various administrations.
- Interview with John D. Lynch, 25 August 2008; OH 396-056; Sound Recording, digital, 409 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Lynch, a former Montana legislator from Butte, Montana, discusses his family history and the events leading up to his work in Montana politics. He describes campaigning in Butte, his work on the House Appropriations Committee, the influence of the Montana Power Company and the Anaconda Company on Montana politics, and discusses governors that he served with including Tom Judge, Ted Schwinden, Stan Stephens, and Marc Racicot. He recalls other issues including a coal moratorium and term limits.
- Interview with Joe Mazurek, 25 September 2008; OH 396-057; Sound Recording, digital, 384 MB, Wav; Transcript, leaves
  Mazurek, a former Montana State Senator and gubernatorial candidate, discusses his involvement in ASUM [Associated Students of the University of Montana] while attending The University of Montana-Missoula. He briefly discusses influential politicians through his years in the Montana Senate, the Montana Power Company and Anaconda Company’s role in Montana politics, various lobbyists, controversial bills, and past governors, Ted Schwinden and Stan Stephens.
- Interview with Greg Jergeson, 29 July 2009; OH 396-058; Sound Recording, digital, 454 MB, Wav; Transcript, 33 leaves
  Jergeson, a former Montana State senator, describes his over thirty years, beginning in the 1970s, in the Montana State Senate, mostly in terms of fellow politicians. He talks about Francis Bardanouve’s mentorship during the early part of his political career. He also reminisces about fellow legislators including Fred Van Valkenburg, John Mercer, Bruce Crippen and Governors Judge, Schwinden, Racicot, Stevens and Martz.
- Interview with Mike Halligan, 29 July 2009; OH 396-059; Sound Recording, digital, 409 MB, Wav; Transcript, 31 leaves
  Halligan, a former Montana State Senator, lieutenant gubernatorial candidate and lobbyist, discusses his twenty years (1980-2000) serving in the Montana State Senate and why he became involved in politics. He talks about fellow legislators (Chet Blaylock, Jean Turnage, Francis Bardanouve, Bill Norman, Joe Mazurek, and Bruce Crippen) and lobbyists with whom he worked and reflects on Governors Schwinden, Stephens, Racicot, Martz and Schweitzer. He talks about the Montana Power Company’s influence and describes work on de-regulation, sales tax and term-limits and talks about his run for the lieutenant governorship with gubernatorial candidate Dorothy Bradley.
- Interview with Fred Van Valkenburg, 23 June 2009; OH 396-060; Sound Recording, 475 digital, MB, Wav; Transcript, 27 leaves
  Van Valkenburg, a Missoula County County Attorney, former Montana State Senator, and former Montana State Senate Majority Leader, describes his Catholic upbringing and how that along with John Kennedy’s presidency inspired him to run for public office. He reminisces about his years as the Montana Senate’s Majority Leader and serving with Representatives Jean Turnage, Matt Himsl, Francis Bardanouve and others. He discusses working with Montana governors Tom Judge, Ted Schwinden, Stan Stephens, Marc Racicot. He recalls legislation like de-regulation and the coal tax.
- Interview with Dan W. Harrington, 8 October 2009; OH 396-061; Sound Recording, digital, 491 MB, Wav; Transcript, 47 leaves
  Harrington, a former Montana state legislator and Montana Constitutional Convention delegate, discusses the Anaconda Company and its influence on Butte, mining operations, and Montana state politics. He describes deregulation of electricity in the state and Montana Power Company lobbyists. He also talks about the 1972 Montana Constitutional Convention and the changes made to the constitution that affected the Anaconda Company.
- Interview with Dorothy Bradley, 29 September 2009; OH 396-062; Sound Recording, digital, 451 MB, Wav; Transcript, 38 leaves
  Bradley, a former Montana state legislator, and state gubernatorial candidate, describes the events that drew her to run for the Montana House of Representatives at the age of 23. She talks about being the only woman in the Montana House in 1971 and her introduction of the abortion bill in Montana. She discusses fellow legislators including John Hall, Dan Yardley, Ken Nordtvedt, Francis Bardanouve, and Mike Halligan. She recalls her environmental activism as a representative and her unsuccessful campaign for governor in 1992.
- Interview with Daniel Kemmis, 9 December 2009; OH 396-063; Sound Recording, digital, 385 MB, Wav; Transcript, 23 leaves
  Kemmis, a former Montana state legislator and former Speaker of the Montana House of Representatives, reminisces about his family’s politics and his college years at Harvard and how they influenced him to run for public office. He talks about Montana governors Tom Judge and Ted Schwinden. He discusses different lobbyists with whom he worked and the role the Anaconda Company and the Montana Power Company played in Montana politics.
- Interview with Fred Thomas, 31 March 2010; OH 396-064; Sound Recording, digital, 479 MB, Wav; Transcript, 35 leaves
  Thomas, a former Montana state senator and gubernatorial candidate, discusses his 20-plus years serving in the Montana State Legislature. He describes how his family’s involvement in politics encouraged him to become a politician. He briefly talks about fellow legislators including Elmer Severson, Bill Groff, Bob Marks, Jack Ramirez, and Bob Thoft. He also discusses his introduction of the deregulation bill and its effect on Montana’s economy.
- Interview with John Mercer, 2 April 2010; OH 396-065; Sound Recording, digital, 451 MB, Wav; Transcript, 30 leaves